welcome to the fifth episode of BC under
the hood so a while ago we had another
episode where we talked about how many
users can business Central handle in the
cloud and what we said back then is
there are a lot of resources in the
cloud a lot of compute and a lot of
database so business Central can
actually handle many users
providing we write good L code so we are
going to talk about performance today
and we are going to talk about how to
write super fast s code my name is
Vincent Nicholas I am the Chief
Architect of business Central and today
with me to talk about performance I have
invited bad yeah I'm B nutsen and I have
been with a product for many years I
started writing AO code in
Seaside and now I'm part of of a
Vincent's a Architects or app Architects
so actually when you uh started it
wasn't Al back then right in seide it
was C was C yes you you you have been
working with the B up for many many
years many years so about um what
um what can happen in in in in in you
know to that that will affect
performance yeah so now that we talk
about performance uh I think we should
take a look at how how fast is it and
where do we spend our time mhm and a few
years ago I did some
measurements so executing a line of Al
code or a statement that doesn't look up
in the database takes approximately a
microc seconds that means a million
lines per second that's really fast and
these are even Advanced um statements
like calculations or assignments or yeah
then we have SQL calls and at best they
are one
millisecond uh often it's seconds I mean
full seconds but even a millisecond is
thousand times a microsc
right then I also looked at our code and
um the ratio
between database statements and non
database statements is approxim
approximately 10 to one if you combine
these numbers it means that basically
the NST spends 99% of its time just
waiting for the database to return with
the
result so way the time goes yes so that
mean quite important what's happening
with the database exactly so it's all
about database access that's the only
thing we really care
about actually um you know we have some
automated tests where we compare version
to version or even build to build when
we as the project goes
forward and the only only thing we are
we care about there is the number of
database calls because the timing can
vary uh for various
reasons count how many database we can
do that with the performance tool kit
okay which we encourage people to use so
also also Partners can do that with it's
fre accessible and it shows will show
you both uh timings which obviously
users are interested in but also the
number of seal statements MH y so yeah
so okay so now we so database database
is where most of the time goes exactly
so any good or bad code has to do with
how well do we manage our database
access so we talk about so one of the
things we're we're talking about uh we
talked about in this previous uh episode
was long running queries yes how long
does a query have to be before we we
categorize it as a long run query yeah
so well we say when it's longer than 750
milliseconds then we Define it is long
enough to be interesting for us to log
and then we log in there so anything
that's under that takes less than 7 15
second we consider normal yeah we
applying to that would see
um yeah but what is long um what is
expensive I
mean a bread can be expensive and a car
can be cheap right even it's completely
different yes it depends what we do if
you do something very complex Maybe it's
okay yeah exactly I can do complex
report or something but uh some other
operations can be considered maybe more
uh should be immediate from the user
standpoint at so generally speaking the
more often you query the database
obviously mhm and the more time the DAT
database needs to spend reading data or
fetching the data the database is like
librarian right going fetch stuff for
you uh so what can we do about long War
inqueries let's say we we detect a
really bad one like several seconds or
even you know even sometimes you know
minutes uh that can happen to yeah
that's where what can we do about it we
can first of all look at indexing mhm
and I first of all we need to detect it
yeah
and um that's where Telemetry comes into
play obviously we have a lot of
customers we can look into in Telemetry
form
mhm uh but as partners you would have
app insights mhm where you can uh at
least look at your
customers but also if you have a
specific customer complaining about a
specific case then you can go and
investigate that both with app insights
but also with some of the tools that are
built into the product um so index index
optimization index optimization and and
first of all detecting the that's the
query that that yeah
understanding that the query is is is
taking time and then we can do index
indexing that that might be missing
indexes for example that's one thing but
also the structure of the code uh how
often do we actually have a slide yeah
it show something
here
so here I have a slide that shows you
ways to minimize the number of
queries so for instance um nested Loops
you know you loop our all customers and
for each customer you do something
something look something up or if it's
posting a lot of sales invoices you do a
lot of stuff per sales invoice and per
sales line so what you're saying
actually is that um if I understand
correctly one thing is queries which you
can do one single query which will take
a long time which is bad yes but also
you can have many smaller queries that
even though they don't take a lot of
time they they might be for example in
Loop or even nested loop as you mention
right maybe it's a bad analogy but think
of you go to Sho door mhm right yeah
and you come in the exact pair you
wanted in the right size are there on
display and you say you take them and
you're happy that that corresponds to
hitting the NST cache if you will like
the NST already has it there here you
go um the next level is um you say could
you go and fetch a pair of these for me
in my size size whatever 40
and then the clerk goes off M comes back
and you try them on and say ah not quite
right and off he goes again
or so that's one that could be multiple
queries right or you up front say I'm
I'm interested in these three pairs mhm
and I'm sure not sure whether my size is
40 no two three or four mhm could you go
and fetch all for me m and then it will
go off and
take everything back of course you'll
spend more time on storage but oh it's
going to be faster exactly so each round
trip actually is round trip is the one
of the bad guys here so we want to avoid
having many round trips for example in
Loop yeah exactly and that's where we
can use queries because that can do um
combine the loops if you will and it can
do summarizations and all sorts of good
things for us the other thing is we can
use flow fields which is also kind of an
old-fashioned um that has been around
for a long time is yeah forever
almost um so for instance you have an
look something up and you want you know
sum the sum of all underlying entries
that's typically a flow field or if it's
an entry you may have the um account
name or customer name as a flow field a
lookup flow field and you can ask SQL to
you know calculate these as the I mean
in instantly so as opposed to doing it
in the code yeah yeah exactly instead of
doing it afterwards with Cal fields and
yeah so basically the strategy you are
describing here is to push as much as
possible to SQL yes because SQL is quite
good at doing this kind of thing SQL
itself is blistering fast that's what
SQL is it's very good at doing this kind
of operations I mean the biggest
companies in the world run a SQL serus
it's not because it's slow right right
so it's better to to let SQL do that
kind of thing aggregation of calculation
of fields kind of thing exactly rather
than we try trying to do it in the in
the yeah so that's one thing and the
last thing is a smaller smaller thing
but we can use the function called set
load Fields so some of our records are
very large and even some of them have
extensions MH but if you're only
interested in I don't know a posting
group or a currency code for a customer
you don't need to read the entire
customer record with all its extensions
you can ask see could only go and fetch
that currency code instead of returning
the entire yeah and having to do joints
and everything with yeah exactly that's
also yeah uh something we can do it
should do so how how can I so so you you
gave a few examples of how to write
better code here faster code so how can
I um or can I do a Baseline and what's
the best way to figure out you know how
much that helps can I do it before and
after comparison of my code like let's
say I'm read piece of code then I think
doesn't perform very well and I suspect
it's a database and I follow some of
your recommendation maybe do do some
optimization indexing or whatever and
yeah I mean the yeah so the the
performance tool kit I mentioned before
obviously can help you simulate that one
tool um obviously you can also if you
can Repro it locally then you have
access to the database SQL tools like
profiler
mhm um so how much uh talking about
which how much um if I'm a developer U
yeah a BC developer how much do I need
to understand how much knowledge of SQL
do I need how much to understand what
how SQL works and because um if I just
write a code you know I don't see the
queries themselves uh per se right
exactly and this is where I also come to
something else that's fundamental I mean
ideally Al is
um in theory agnostic sequel because our
statements are you know we have get and
F set SE language in nail exactly
exactly and sometimes it's that's a good
thing sometimes not but it's really
useful to understand at least the
indexing uh part so what what happens
under the hood basically when we compile
Al and the run time we actually do
generate somewhere we do gener a SQL
statement right uh but you you kind of
never see it as a as but what's
happening somewhere when you ride a a g
or it's even better than that actually
because even before issuing a SQL
statement uh the NST will see do I
already have this data in my cache so
typically for um when you do get you
know get some setup get this customer or
something if it's popular enough it will
be there in the cache um so it it would
be an inmemory operation which is close
to instant
uh but otherwise whatever we write is
transformed into some kind of
Sequel and this is also a place where we
um uh optimize over the years also as
SQL becomes more and more advanced we
try to adapt that and uptake new SQL
features so the first time you typically
the first time you would be the record
setad of records that would be maybe a
little bit slow it will at least take a
millisecond yeah and then then we will
have it in the cache yes and if
subsequent request we requesting same
will be very fast so that's maybe why
people or that that is why people
experiencing sometimes when you just log
on in in the fresh instance of and
nobody else has logged on before yeah um
and what's more it's not just your
session it's the company's session right
so if none of your colleagues if you if
you're at the first Monday morning yeah
then you get to load everything into
cash so that's your so an advice is is
don't don't come too early at work
exactly
yeah Monday you should start at 10:
before like everybody has has actually
hydrated the cash so no that's not
that's all caching obviously also
metadata and pages and what have
you so um no for what they need I have
um another slide here actually um
because when you retrieve data from the
database obviously it has to do with the
amount of data the bigger the table the
more records the longer it
takes so there are like four levels um
of fetching a record one is the what we
call primary key lookup that's like the
get you know get this entry with this
pair of shoes that you get by way the
almost so that's as fast as it can get
because yeah the next one is what we
call index seek so we know it's a number
you know whatever one to three or it is
MH and then the SQL go and find an
perfectly matching index and find it
exactly and see oh this it's located
there and then it will read it for you
mhm um the third level which is not good
is that the field is in an index but
it's not in the beginning of the index
and the only thing SQL can do then is it
has to read through the entire index
which can be millions of if it's a Lar
yeah I mean for all entry tables it will
be Millions MH uh that's really
bad um so can we avoid
that yes and no yes of course we can
just add an index for that field MH
mhm but sometimes some customers want to
search on all sorts of fields and we
can't have an index for each field yeah
because index are also a little bit
expensive right they are expensive both
in maintenance but also in uh volume I
mean database uh dis space so is that
fair to say also that like as a rule of
thumb indexes are helping for speed for
retrieval of data but when insert new
data it's actually a little more
expensive than if you don't have an
index right you have to you don't only
insert the data you also have to
maintain the index at the same time
exactly but that's that's kind of a
price to pay to get a fast retrieval
yeah later on yeah I mean any way in
that sense it's exactly
like a book or encyclopedia right you
with a lot of Articles you need to find
an article about whatever MH and if you
can you know an alphabetic index find it
quickly is fine MH if it's not sorted
alphabetically then you would need to go
through the entire index to find it
which obviously takes a long time yeah
and the worst is if there is no index
then you need to read the book or at
least yeah browse the book which comes
is the corresponds to the fourth
um uh case where we have a table scan
okay so full table scan is the absolute
worst that's the worst yeah when does
that happen typically that happens
typically I mean obviously when we don't
have an index but it also most people
experience it when they um use the um in
a page you know list page in the upper
left corner upper right you
mean uh
whatever this is left for the for the
viewer okay okay okay all right
right uh there's this page search field
right where you can enter stuff right I
want to find Vincent like made my
customer list but since I have a
thousand um not a thousand maybe a
million customers in the list and the
Page search actually searches on all
visible
columns okay except for numbers and
booleans and stuff like that they will
search the name field it will search the
address field it'll search you know
whatever City
Field um and the only way the sequel can
handle that is by actually reading
through all million customers and that
takes forever which people have that's
explains why this feature is
particularly slow yes and does that also
so when a users does that system do a
search like this yeah does it actually
impact other users in the
system yes and no
only not by locking or anything but of
course it takes some resources away from
SQL right we'll get to locking in a
second yeah exactly right because SQL
needs to spend time reading the entire
customer record or table so we're using
so that one user is going to use some of
the database resources some database
computational resources so that could
explain why other users find the system
slow while true SQL is searching
especially if several people are doing
this at the same time as they typically
would in a system so don't come early in
the morning and and and don't use a stem
while somebody else is searching yeah or
instead of doing the Page search if you
have a lot of data Maybe use the column
filtering if you know it's the name then
at least you can filter on the name say
I want to find Vincent in the name field
yeah so that helps AB the customer the
last thing I think we want to spend a
little bit of time is locking yeah
because that's also one of the as we
talked about in in the other episode
that's also one of the things that can
uh create some uh some perceived bad
performance on the system uh so what's
uh tell us a little bit about it what
what is it what what is locking when
does it happen you know what what
triggers it yeah I mean locking is a
good thing as such it's a good feature
that sequel as invented why why it
doesn't sound good like why would I lock
something right if I want to update some
stuff I may want to say nobody touches
this and nobody touches this until I'm
done because otherwise I get an
inconsistent transaction right so for
example just to if let's say I update
the uh the customer address yeah so uh I
first update say the street name yeah
and then afterwards I update the let's
say the uh postcode yeah and the town
you don't want somebody fetching that
record while before I'm done exactly
otherwise I will have like the old the
new address uh the street name and the
old post code and town name exactly and
then a totally wrong address so abut
that's a corrupted data so that's why
when an operation like this happens we
need to kind of lock that recall and in
particular when we get into um posting
stuff or you know bigger updates uh that
we come in come to in a in a bit we
really want to make sure that this
transaction is consistent so as such
locking is a good thing but we also
spend a lot of time looking up stuff and
calculating stuff and looking more stuff
up and writing lock entries and doing
stuff that um we should do before we
actually start updating the let's say
the shared resources so good pattern is
to do all the expensive stuff first mhm
and then at the very end do a quick
update update so so I was going to ask
you about this because you discover
quite recently or a while ago you
discovered that in in our application
there there are many places where we
don't quite follow that pattern right
where we where we take a look on on on
some of the data very early in the
process and uh in effect that means that
uh a lot of people a lot of users are
potentially waiting yes I mean we can
take a look at the sales order process
posting because that's like our
canonical example always we use and um
if we look at what happens when post a
sales
order uh it's like in two steps first
you do some internal calculations um
calculate discounts and tax and stuff
like that but then we go and fetch um a
number from a number series which is a
shared resource and then we commit and
then we remember this mhm document
number we got and then we start creating
U or going through all the lines posting
to inventory and resources and what have
you and during all that time the so what
is locked during that time yeah so
that's the problem because um we don't
know if order a has something with in
items and then resources and then
something else or another order has
resources items something else and we
don't want Deadlocks right so just to be
sure we take a semaphor lock if you will
mhm basically locking the system out for
anyone else mhm I mean when it comes to
posting so just that table or how much
do we actually lock in that process we
from then on WE lock only what we need
but the problem is that this is a
semaphore lock we're saying now we we
are alone in this big room nobody else
can come in here everybody we close the
door nobody this is Supermarket only I
can be in the supermarket at the time
until I'm done mhm what we really want
obviously
going forward is to allow more people in
the supermarket at the same time if you
will right
yeah uh but if you look at what happens
is that we spend short time maybe 10% of
the time doing what I said first then
90% of the time is you know what we call
the po actual posting where we lock
everybody else
out
and this may not be long this might be
one second or 5 Seconds which is not
long but if several people post at the
same
time you know number user number two
will have to wait the 5 seconds until
the user number one is done right yeah
user number three will have to wait 5 +
5 5 + 5 and that this very quick
compounds so he like standing at the que
to get back to supermarket analogy like
if you have 10 customers and they all
take you know 10 minutes to go through
the cashier you have to wait you know
the number of customers time 10 for
before you get you get served right
exactly uh so this is how it is now and
obviously we want to get us to a
situation like this
where where we actually can do things at
least more in parallel I mean things
like getting a number sequence might be
serialized but that's like a few
milliseconds so we don't care about that
yeah because the code itself the code
the code itself in in theory could run
in parallel yes like technically there's
no there's no reason I mean it is a
multi-user system exactly it is parallel
system right we have several processors
in the machines so so we have the I mean
technically it should be possible to run
some of these things in parall and and
most things are actually concurrent
because you going to have five users
editing five different customers at the
same time or five other entities you
know hundreds I mean yeah as long as you
as long as we don't go and touch the
same data item at the same time so it's
not only about being in different tables
it's also about staying away from each
other's
um records but we do also have a uh a
lock um a page where we can see all the
locks right yeah in the products yes we
have a number of very good tools we have
obviously the database locks page that
shows what happens now then we have the
missing indexes page which shows SQL
suggestions we have the in client
profiler that where the user can record
an action and get a profile and then we
have application insights and these are
all well documented and displayed
elsewhere but specifically for the
incline profiler I'll point to that you
can download the profile file and open
it in Visual Studio code and get you
know very nice overview of where time is
spent it it's a huge helper um when you
analyze customer cases actually recently
we have got uh some new features MH so
if I as a as a deop developer as I said
in the example before
um I can use the new read isolation
feature okay so even though you know
where I'm called from the customer be
may be in a locking mhm scope if you
will I can say now I want to read the
customer record without locking only
reading um committed data or uncommitted
or
whatever
that's maybe not a game changer but at
least it will so that's the feature we
introduced already a while ago yeah it's
it was in 202 maybe yeah yeah we'll put
some some links in the in the
description and documentation
so that's um something we really need to
we and partners need to uptake uh we
relevant but that is gamechanging when
it comes to making the system uh
concurrent right if you will so let's
get back to the the tools uh we're
saying we have some we have some tools
for some some some help for for
preventing loing yeah at least finding
diagnosed as troubleshooting and
preventing right exactly so um um
Christian in his in a similar talk last
time mhm uh actually mentioned all of
them yes or most of them yeah but maybe
we can recap I'll recap them and I have
them here um so we have the database
locks page which shows you um who is
locking now mhm the problem for me if I
were a partner is that you know the
customer calls
complains um but I don't I may not have
access to this system and I can of
course Inu him to go and look right but
by then the locks may may be gone right
so it's like it's only interesting when
it happens mhm so you need yes you need
to be to have some some access to the
system for yeah for seeing for to be
able to see that page yeah and you need
to look at it when it happens yes yes
afterwards it's it's gone right it's
like an accident that's yeah over yeah
yeah um then Christian also mentioned
the missing indexes page and that's um
statistics if you will because different
customers have different data
distributions and different
patterns so this is actually a feature
of SQL right that we are surfacing into
a yeah exactly so SQL has as the ability
to monitor the queries that are
performed yeah and uh sometimes so you
we don't we don't know all the queries
we know the queries from our code from
the macrosoft code there might be there
usually a set of extensions other
Solutions on top some queries we don't
know about uh which we cannot optimize
up front for and um and SQL has this
feature where where it monitors what's
going on in the system and can advise
and what's even better or more is that
we collect all collect data from all the
SQL servers all our servers um and
combine it into a dashboard so we can
actually see
combined um which indexes are missing
most so you can actually get
recommendation from also coming from
other systems or yeah all our systems
all our customers right which is way
better than looking at one specific
customer obviously as a partner you
would look at your customer right and
optimize it for them but we as Microsoft
need to optimize for everybody yeah
everybody or the average or the 80% or
whatever
yeah um then we have the incline
performance profiler which is a gem uh
that I think many people are not looking
enough at yeah yeah we can see that in
our Telemetry that we don't have a lot
of usage on and I will in a second
that's why we keep advertising for so
please use it you why you should use it
in a second uh and then obviously
application insights because that's
where you can see long run inqueries you
get the call Stacked you can see exactly
you know what we're trying to query and
whether it's locking or not and so on
but to get back to the incline profiler
in there you can actually download a
file profile file that you can open in
Visual Studio code mhm uh it may need to
activate some feature or I can't
remember but again put some links into
the do but the point is uh then you can
get um something like this where you
where we're running a report and for
some reason it takes like 16 seconds I
think says here on have to get each row
so that's a very long it's that's
extremely long right and then you can
see okay there's a function that spends
8 seconds itself but then the other 8
seconds are distributed and then you can
see okay you can pinpoint exactly which
three or four functions you want to look
at and then you can go look at your code
so yeah so in that case the H second
function is probably the uh the one you
want to look at yeah or all four of them
we don't know the point you can go and
you can go all the way to the code right
with this tool yeah and pinpoint the
exact exactly line of code almost that
this
uh function level but even so function
level yeah but even down to a function
so so it's you know that but even so
this is a gem I mean use it use it I say
all right all right um together with app
insights obviously yeah all right so
what um so we do we have any new uh up
coming performance Improvement or
tooling you know what that can that we
will soon be releasing or can you about
that yeah so one of the big blockers we
have
is um if you go back to the posting mhm
so you have been working on that
recently yes uh so if you look at
entries you know typically in when we
create ledge entries G entries Warehouse
entries
whatever we have a pattern uh where we
basically lock the table mhm and then
only I can add to this table mhm and of
course it means that all entries are
coming in nice buckets and when you say
we you mean in the base app Microsoft
yes Microsoft yes yeah so what we do is
I mean most Partners who know all this
this already but we go out find the last
entry and then we just count up one
right to create new entries and
insert and while we do this we're
locking the table and I have a picture
here that kind of illustrates that we
have some Warehouse entries with
different colors that belong from
different transactions that are linked
to the warehouse register and they're
color
coded what we want to get to is
um to use um number sequences as the
generator for entry numbers MH we could
also have considered um using Auto
increment which I guess most partners
are aware of as well but the basic point
is that um by using some kind of
non-locking assignment of Entry numbers
whether be it number sequences or Auto
increment we can actually have several
users creating um transactions at the
same time at the same time yeah and uh
as Illustrated on this picture
um there will be some mixing of the um
entries mhm but that's maybe okay that's
fine um maybe not for
GL because some country there are all
kinds of legislations but all other
tables who
cares uh so for bc25 in October release
we actually have done this for warehouse
entries and which means that from there
we can have separate uh or Sate
concurrent posting to Warehouse entry uh
Warehouse system at the same time so
people working in the warehouse can do
stuff even while
the um people in the office do other
stuff so so yeah we talked about some of
the scenarios where yeah people have F
scanning bar code yeah exactly all these
SC long response time which is
experience right exactly it's um it must
be horrible to be in the warehouse and
your screen locks up right so with that
with that new feature Improvement of the
code that should that should help right
yes should uh but as I said this is just
the first step we have a you know a
bucket list of Entry tables we need to
fix this before we can get
to fully concurrent posting of sales
holders so by the way if you're
interested in these changes you can
follow we open source we have open
source so we you can you can follow
what's going on and all the pool request
that is doing around this you can
you can check this out if if you should
interested in definitely the warehouse R
stuff that's already there so that's
been there for I know month yeah yeah so
is there any other features we should
look forward to or other performance um
you know improvements or Performance
Tools that are coming in future yes yes
um so very on a very short time frame we
uh we are going to try to solve the
issue of Page
search by introducing the SQL s full
text indexing meaning that hopefully
from pc25 searching in a customer list
will be very quick MH also I mean items
as well obviously but also when you are
on a sales line and you you know start
entering the item number and you get
this drop down list that should be very
fast as
well um on a longer Horizon we think the
concurrence and parall ation is the big
thing to do because that's the promise
of the cloud if you will MH and often we
focus on how long does it take to post
the sales order but that's not the issue
right doesn't matter whether it takes
one second or 5 seconds because if
you're going to post 50,000 of them or
adj just cost for 50,000 items it needs
to be paralyzed you need to do that and
you know if you just cutting it in half
like two threads right is huge right
four I mean if you can cut cut it down
two hours from eight by just having four
processes is fantastic so that's you
know a path we are some we could look
forward to and I mean which we started
with the um Warehouse stuff right we all
right all right thanks B so um we hope
that you got some hints on how to write
super fast the other code we try to give
you some um some indication how you
could improve your solution and your
code we'll put some links in the
description about some of the things we
talked about here and um we hope we
enjoy you enjoyed that that episode let
us know in the comments thank you for
watching thank you